Register of the Antonina Dmitrievna Ignat'eva papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Antonina Dmitrievna Ignat'eva papers
1907-1967
2018C11
Hoover Institution Archives
3 manuscript boxes (1.2 linear feet)
Diaries, correspondence, fictional and other writings, personal documents, printed matter, and photographs relating to the Russian Civil War in Siberia, and to Russian émigré affairs. Includes papers of other family members.
Ignat'eva, Antonina Dmitrievna
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual or digital material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2017.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Russian resident of Chita, Siberia; subsequently émigré in the United States.
1900 29 April Born, Chita, Transbaikal Province, Russian Empire
1919 19 November Married Vladimir Romanovich Torchinov
1920 15 November Birth of daughter Zina
1922-1923 Lived in Qingdao (Tsingtao), China
1923 7 October Arrived in the United States (Seattle, Washington)
1926 30 November Moved to Los Angeles, California
1930 Last name changed from Torchinov to Torchin
1972 13 June Death of Vladimir Torchin
1982 2 January Died, Los Angeles, California
Scope and Content of Collection
Biographical materials, diaries, correspondence, writings, printed matter, and photographs, relating to Russians in Chita (Transbaikal Province) during the Revolution and Civil War (1917-1921), in China and the United States. Includes papers of other Ignat’ev Ignatieff family members.
This collection consists mainly of the writings and fragments of writings of Antonina (Nina) Dimitrievna Ignat’eva, the daughter of a rich Chita merchant, who from her school days was actively engaged in amateur literary and dramatic activities in Chita and Los Angeles. The most historically significant part of the collection is the diaries she kept in Chita from late June 1917 to late May 1918, November 1918 to February 1919, and a diary fragment covering late October to early November 1920. Through the eyes of a young adult one sees the spread of revolution in the Russian Far East and the subsequent civil war. Since her future husband was an adjutant to Ataman G. M. Semenov, she was also able to observe Semenov’s domestic life.
Russia--Emigration and immigration.; Russians--United States.; Siberia (Russia)--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1922 (Box 1)
  - Educational records, 1922 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    Contains a notebook on cosmetic dermatology
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1923-1931 and undated (Box 1)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - Unidentified, 1923-1931 and undated (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Grandmother, 1931 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Ignat’ev (Ignatieff), Aleksandr and Mikhail Dimitrievich (brothers), 1923-1926 and undated (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Ignat’eva, Mariia Dionis’evna (mother), undated (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Kulaev (Koulaieff), Ivan Vasil’evich, 1926 (Box-folder 1: 6)
- DIARIES, 1917-1930 (Box 1)
  Daily entries, notes and inserts arranged chronologically
  - Journal, 1917-1919. (Box-folder 1: 7)
    Holograph. Contains records of class schedule, sculpting lessons, theater attendance, and other activities.
  - Diary, 1917-1918. (Box-folder 1: 8)
    Holograph. Contains entries from 27 Jun. 1917 – 21 May 1918. Also includes two interpolations from 1930.
  - Diary, 1918-1919. (Box-folder 1: 9)
    Holograph. Contains entries from 25 Nov. 1918 – 4 Feb. 1919
  - Diary, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 10)
    Holograph. Contains entries from 22 Oct. – 10 Nov. 1920
  - Diary, 1927-1930. (Box-folder 1: 11)
    Holograph. Contains entries from 12 Jul. 1927 – 15 Nov. 1930
- WRITINGS, 1916-1932 and undated (Box 1-2)
  Fragments, plays and short stories, arranged chronologically by title
  - General (Box 1)
    - Fragments, undated. (Box-folder 1: 12-37)
      Holograph and typescript. Includes untitled fragments of brief plays, short stories, sketches and notes
  - “Admiral Kolchak i Semenov,”, undated. (Box-folder 2: 1)
    Holograph
  - “A Few Words about Paul Bern,”, undated. (Box-folder 2: 2)
    Typescript
  - “Desiat’ liet tomu nazad,”, undated. (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - “Drakony. Shutka v odnom deistvie,”, undated. (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - “Etiud,”, undated. (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - “Imenitoe kupechestvo. P’esa v 3-kh deistviiakh,”, undated. (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - “Lebed’,”, undated. (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - “Maiorat. (Kratkii konspekt romana),”, undated. (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - “Nervy. (Iz zapisnoi knizhki),”, undated. (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - “Sadko (iz derevni). Komediia v odnom deistvii i trekh kartinakh,”, undated. (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - “S bol’shoi dorogi,”, undated. (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - “Sol’ tsaritsy,”, undated. (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - “Stranitsy iz voennoi zhizni,”, undated. (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - “Tsyganskiia nastroeniia. Muzykal’naia pantomima,”, undated. (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - “Tysiacha vtoraia noch’,”, undated. (Box-folder 2: 15)
    Holograph and typescript
  - “Vengeance. Etude,”, undated. (Box-folder 2: 16)
    Holograph. Also includes a draft letter to an unnamed editor
  - “V kasting offisie. (Russian interview),”, undated. (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - “Iz t’my k svietu,”, 1916 (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - “Ia prines na tvoi grob belosnezhnye rozy. Novella,”, 1919 (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - “On i ona. Novella,”, 1919 (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - “Pod zaborom. (Iz zhizni bogemy). (Etiud),”, 1920 (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - “Tanagrskiia statuetki. (S natury),”, 1921 (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - “Nikto,”, 1924 (Box-folder 2: 23)
  - “Nobody,”, 1924 (Box-folder 2: 24)
  - “Pin’-Din’. Ddramaticheskii etiud v 1 d. i 3 kart. (Iz zakulisnoi zhizni),”, 1925 (Box-folder 2: 25)
  - “Olvais’,”, 1926 (Box-folder 2: 26)
  - “Osenniia nastroeniia,”, 1926 (Box-folder 2: 27)
  - Untitled, 1926 (Box-folder 2: 28)
  - “Liubov’ i svoboda. Novella,”, 1927 (Box-folder 2: 29)
  - “Korabli. (Rozhdestvenskaia novella),”, 1928 (Box-folder 2: 30)
  - “Russkii byt. (Komediia v odnom deistvii),”, 1929 (Box-folder 2: 31)
  - Untitled adaptation of the fairy tale “Sleeping Beauty” for the stage (in Russian), 1929 (Box-folder 2: 32-33)
    Holograph and typescript. See also PRINTED MATTER/Programs for the 1930 production at the Russian Women’s Aid Society of Los Angeles
  - “Bezprizornaia. Muzykal’naia drama-misteriia,”, 1930 (Box-folder 2: 34)
  - Untitled, 1930 (Box-folder 2: 35)
  - “Greza bielaia,”, 1932 (Box-folder 2: 36)
- WRITINGS BY OTHERS, 1919 and undated. (Box 2)
  Arranged alphabetically by author
  - Anonymous, “U lukomor’ia dub srubili…,”, undated. (Box-folder 2: 37)
    Holograph. An adaptation of the Prologue to A. S. Pushkin’s “Ruslan and Ludmilla” in the form of political satire on Stalin’s regime ca 1935
  - Ghermanoff, George F., “Umiraiushchiia serdtsa,”, undated. (Box-folder 2: 38)
  - Likhachev, Mikhail Mikhailovich, “Mariia,”, 1919 (Box-folder 2: 39)
    Typescript. A brief play featuring Nina Ignat’ev, Vladimir Torchinov, Ataman G. M. Semenov’s wife Mariia, and others
  - Sheshmintsev, Sergei, “Vecherniia grezy,”, undated. (Box-folder 2: 40)
- FAMILY FILE, 1907-1967 and undated. (Box 3)
  Papers of other members of the Ignat’ev (Ignatieff) family, arranged alphabetically by name and therein by physical form
  - Ignat’ev (Ignatieff), Aleksandr Dimitrievich (brother), 1919-1929 (Box 3)
    - Biographical file, 1919-1923 and undated (Box 3)
      - Identity papers, 1923 (Box-folder 3: 1)
      - Military service records, 1919-1922 (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - Correspondence, 1921-1929 and undated (Box 3)
      - Unidentified, 1921-1924 and undated (Box-folder 3: 3)
      - Ignat’eva, Tat’iana Stepanovna, undated (Box-folder 3: 4)
      - Samarina, A., 1923 (Box-folder 3: 5)
      - Semenov, D., 1923 (Box-folder 3: 6)
      - Sheshmintsev, Sergei, 1921-1923 and undated (Box-folder 3: 7)
      - Sheshmintsev, Viktor, 1929 and undated (Box-folder 3: 8)
    - Financial records, 1923 and undated (Box-folder 3: 9)
    - Miscellany, undated (Box-folder 3: 10)
      A notebook listing durable paints and describing various glues, and a set-design drawing
  - Ignat’eva, Mariia Dionis’evna (mother), 1907-1923 and undated (Box 3:)
    - Correspondence (Box 3)
      - General, 1921-1923 and undated (Box-folder 3: 11)
      - Ignat’eva, Nina Dimitrievna, 1917-1922 and undated (Box-folder 3: 12)
      - Kulaev (Koulaieff), Ivan Vasil’evich, 1922 (Box-folder 3: 13)
    - Reminiscences, 1907 (Box-folder 3: 14)
  - Torchinov (Torchinoff, Torchin), Vladimir Romanovich (husband), 1927-1967 and undated (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box-folder 3: 15)
      Letter from V. Chernykh
    - Financial records, 1927-1967 and undated (Box-folder 3: 16)
- PRINTED MATTER, 1914-1937 and undated (Box 3)
  Booklet, clippings, journal, and programs
  - Clippings, undated (Box-folder 3: 17)
    Includes an incomplete clipping from an unidentified Chita newspaper regarding the confiscation of Ignat’ev family property
  - From Letters of Congratulation to I. V. Koulaieff on His Eightieth Birthday, January 20, 1937, n.l., n.p. (Box-folder 3: 18)
  - Programs, 1930 and undated. (Box-folder 3: 19)
    Includes program to Nina D. Ignat’eva’s (Torchina’s) adaptation and staging of “Sleeping Beauty”
  - Solntse Rossii, (St. Petersburg, Russia) (Box-folder 3: 20)
    1914: #232(29)-233(30) [incomplete], 247(45), 249(46)-252(49), 255(52) and six unnumbered issues
- PHOTOGRAPHS, undated [circa 1919-1920] (Box 3)
  Three prints depicting Nina D. Ignat’eva (Ignatieff), General Grigorii Mikhailovich Semenov, and his adjutant Vladimir Romanovich Torchinov (Torchinoff)
  - Ignat’eva (Ignatieff), Nina Dimitrievna, undated (Box-folder 3: 21)
    One print
  - Semenov, Grigorii Mikhailovich, undated [ca 1919-1920]. (Box-folder 3: 22)
    One print depicting General Semenov with an unidentified Japanese officer. The print is pasted to a portion of an album page. On the reverse are photographs of two unidentified individuals.
  - Torchinov (Torchinoff), Vladimir Romanovich, undated [ca 1920] (Box-folder 3: 23)